Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady has always wanted to go out.
But now she's been in bed all day.
Didn't you hear the imperial doctor say
My Lady feels more sleepy because she is pregnant?
His Majesty is so attentive.
He visits her every day.
Of course, My Lady is at the very center of His Majesty's heart.
I can tell His Majesty would be overjoyed
even if My Lady gives birth to a princess.
Nonsense!
My Lady will give birth to a prince.
What's the use of having a princess?
Don't jinx My Lady.
Prince! Prince! Prince!
Of course it's a prince.
My Lady, His Majesty is here!
His Majesty is here.
I hear you.
My Lady, please get ready to greet His Majesty.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
You're still having the medicine.
How are you feeling?
Your ...
I thank Your Majesty.
I often feel fatigued and the imperial doctors
advised me to have more rest.
Let's sit down and talk.
I see that your complexion has improved a lot.
I thank Your Majesty for caring.
I owe this to Dr. Wen's meritorious service.
Meizhuang.
It was all my fault.
Your Majesty is the Son of Heaven.
The Son of Heaven is never wrong.
When you've fully recovered I'll ask
Attendance Services to present your name tag.
I'll head back now.
Yes.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
His Majesty departs.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace to Your Majesty.
I knew you were faking.
You are so bad at it. Your eyelashes were fluttering.
No, you woke me up.
The scar seems to look a bit lighter.
I've become the famous ugly maid Zhong Wuyan.
Stop looking at me.
Have you tried all the medicines I sent you?
I have.
It will be entirely gone very soon.
Your beauty is incomparable throughout the world.
I have a younger sister.
Her name is Yurao.
She is "the beauty of the nation".
She is no less beautiful than me.
If so,
I must see her.
That's not allowed.
If you see her,
you will want to make her a concubine immediately
and forget about me.
A woman that makes you jealous.
She must be the most beautiful lady in history.
Maybe it's time for me to have a new concubine.
Tell me,
what title should I grant her?
Noble Lady? Imperial Concubine?
Or directly to Consort?
It's just that my sister is ...
not even ten years old.
Do you have a problem with that?
What's on your mind?
I was thinking this is probably what a peaceful life is.
Huan Huan,
you are carrying my child.
Do you know how happy I am?
I am happy, too.
A pear blossom is white as the snow.
But next to your face it is barely noticeable.
Your skin is as radiant as the snow.
People paint a plum blossom on their forehead,
and call it "the blooming plum".
Pear blossom is white and does not look good when painted on the face.
It might look good.
Really?
What do you think?
It is more graceful than a flower filigree.
But a pear blossom is white.
It doesn’t look real painted with pink.
It's beautiful, even though only an imitation of a pear blossom.
I would like to call it "the adored pear".
Si Lang painted it and named it.
It's very elegant.
I’m afraid the others will think Your Majesty
shows too much favor towards me.
That is obvious.
Does it displease you when I'm partial only to you?
Meizhuang has just recovered.
You Majesty should visit her.
I just did.
But she was cold and distant.
She suffered so long from the plague.
She's been dispirited.
I hope Your Majesty will forgive her if she behaved improperly.
Speaking of the plague,
there's something vexing.
I wonder if Your Majesty could share it with me.
Consort Estime told me that although Drs. Jiang Cheng and
Jiang Shen found an effective remedy for the disease,
they accepted bribes from the servants privately.
They gave priority to treating the powerful
while ignoring the weak which
delayed their treatment and caused their deaths.
"A doctor has the heart of a parent."
They have the skills but not the hearts of doctors.
I'm afraid that is the reason the plague
hasn't fully been eliminated in the palace.
I think so too.
Does Your Majesty remember that they
were also involved in defaming Lady Vertu?
I do.
But the plague is not over.
I have to keep them alive.
I can recommend a doctor to Your Majesty.
He is able to treat the disease.
Who?
The imperial doctor Wen Shichu.
Why?
Dr. Wen developed an effective treatment
when he was taking care of Meizhuang.
And I heard Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen's
prescription came from Dr. Wen's work.
Your Majesty can investigate if you don’t believe it.
Patients treated by Dr. Wen had a faster recovery
without side effects like vomiting and fatigue.
This is because Dr. Jiang used the very
first formula Dr. Wen drafted,
before he made it more gentle.
I would like to meet this Dr. Wen.
If so,
I won't let them live.
Your Majesty,
the plague is just starting to abate
and the entire palace attributes that to the Jiangs.
If Your Majesty removes them now,
I’m afraid it will churn up gossip outside the palace.
Yes.
They are Consort Fleur's people, after all.
But if I'm going remove them there
are plenty of ways to do so.
All right. Let's stop talking about that.
The seventeenth of April is your birthday.
You also just got pregnant.
I would like the Household Department to hold a festive celebration.
I'll follow Your Majesty's decision.
Good, leave it to me.
I will make you and our child happy.
Your Majesty is fond of children
and stays with Consort Fleur frequently.
Why hasn't she become pregnant yet?
She never will be.
I heard that Her Highness had a miscarriage.
Was her health damaged because of that?
I still have some work to do. I'm going
back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Have a good rest.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Xia Yi.
Kill two men for me.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Do it secretly. Don’t arouse any suspicion.
You have done well leading the Flying Guillotine.
Keep a vigilant eye on any signs of
rebellion in the imperial court for me.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Murder!
Murder! Murder!
It's a murder! Run! Run!
Murder! There's a murder!
His Majesty the Emperor.
Your Majesty.
Has Your Majesty heard of the murder of the
imperial doctors Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen?
Their heads were cut off and nowhere to be found.
How can such a bloody crime happen
in the imperial city?
What an intolerable offence to Your Majesty's law!
My beloved consort,
I was shocked when I heard the grievous news as well.
I have ordered immediate investigation of the case.
And in honor of their contribution during the plague,
I will reward their family a hundred taels of silver to fund their funeral.
Don't worry.
But who will take over their work now?
You need not worry about that.
I have ordered imperial doctor Wen Shichu
to take over the treatments.
Congratulations, Dr. Wen.
- Dr. Wen, you have an immeasurably bright future.
- Thank you.
We look forward to receiving your advice and guidance.
Thank you. Likewise.
What do you think of this painting
"Lady Guoguo's Spring Outing"?
Their eyes and brows are very well captured
by the painter. I can see their emotions.
A beauty must have not only an elegant
demeanor but also a perceptive mind.
Otherwise, she would just be a "wooden beauty".
Characterless and uninteresting.
Is that why Your Majesty is so fond of Concubine Sourire?
Her birthday is on the 17th of April.
We have moved to the Summer Palace because
I wanted to hold a celebration to make her happy.
But the protests in Henan Province have just come under control
and I still have a lot to deal with.
I need someone to help me out.
Your Majesty wants me to be in charge of the celebration?
All I could think of was to reward her some rare jewelry.
I'm afraid that she won't be genuinely pleased
unless there's something creative.
You've got to help me come up with some good ideas.
This is a specialty of an idler like me.
Your Majesty need not worry.
This Mudan Pavilion has a lake
to the south and a stream to the west.
The prior emperor Kangxi visited often to enjoy the mudan peonies here.
That's why the pavilion is so well known.
His Majesty holds a celebration for her birthday here.
She is so unworthy of it.
Where is Nobel Prince Guo?
Your Majesty, all the other princes have arrived
but Nobel Prince Guo hasn't shown up.
I'll send someone to check.
Hmm, what a brother!
It seems like we we are unaware of the current makeup trends.
Why do all the noblewomen have
a
pear blossom painted on their foreheads?
That is "the adored pear" His Majesty
designed for Concubine Sourire.
It has started a trend across the city.
Isn't it just like a flower filigree?
It's not even that pretty.
His Majesty personally painted it on Concubine Sourire.
Don't you see his deep affection in that?
Your Majesty,
please allow me to speak to Meizhuang.
Sure.
How come His Majesty is so partial to Concubine Sourire?
His Majesty is not "partial." He has given his heart to her.
Who else can enter the Imperial Study
at any time to serve His Majesty?
Meizhuang, this is your first time
attending a banquet since your recovery.
Are you feeling well?
I'm all right. Don't worry.
Although your health has been restored,
you are not as spirited as before.
I'm really worried about you.
Dr. Wen is an excellent doctor.
But even the great physician Hua Tuo could not cure the heart.
Even if you don't care about His Majesty's favor,
it is crucial to your survival in the palace.
Favor is just a fluke.
"Life changes, like the Yellow River changes its course."
Nothing remains unchanged over time.
So why should I care about His Majesty's volatile favor?
What happened?
Her Ladyship seems unwell.
I'll check on her.
Is Your Ladyship feeling unwell?
I apologize for my lack of etiquette. I have chronic chest pain.
Please sit.
Today is Your Highness's honorable birthday.
I hope I did not dampen Your Highness's spirits.
Your Ladyship must not say that.
Everyone gets sick sometimes.
I hope you will feel better soon.
Does Your Ladyship take Emperor of Heaven's
Special Formula to Tonify The Heart?
Yes, I have the pills with me.
I do not deserve to be helped by Your Highness's noble hands.
We're monarch and subject outside the palace
but a family inside the palace.
Please don't feel like an outsider.
While His Lordship is away for public duties,
Your Ladyship must take care of yourself.
I thank Your Highness for caring.
Is "the adored pear" popular outside the palace?
The women in the city consider it very beautiful.
On the one hand, they can follow Your Highness's makeup.
On the other hand, they believe it will bring
harmony and prosperity to their marriage.
The story has been widely told.
I always heard that Your Highness
is in the highest favor of His Majesty.
But I didn't expect Your Highness to be so gracious.
No wonder His Majesty adores you.
I'm not worthy of Your Ladyship's compliment.
My Lady,
a gift for you prepared by Nobel Prince Guo
is ready to be presented at the rear lake.
His Lordship invites you to go with His Majesty.
Certainly, I'll come now.
I take my leave.
Yunli always comes up with the most pleasant surprises.
I wonder what this one is about.
Let's find out together.
Look!
Congratulations to Your Highness.
Please fly a kite to receive the blessings of Heaven.
Your Majesty, look!
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Mind your step.
How come so many lotuses are blooming in April?
Listen.
"Two Phoenixes Take Flight".
It sounds elegant on the flute.
"Two phoenixes take flight,
resounding a sky of harmony."
A marriage full of joy and harmony is the dream of every woman.
Has your dream come true?
I present the lotus blooms in honor of Concubine Sourire's birthday.
Your Lordship has outdone yourself.
I am deeply honored.
I asked you to devise a novel idea
but I never imagined you would do it so well!
Since Your Majesty entrusted the task to me,
I, of course, did my utmost.
I'm curious how Your Lordship managed to
make the lotuses blossom in the spring.
The lotus roots were planted some time ago.
I diverted water from a hot spring
outside the Summer Palace into the pond.
I thank Your Majesty.
Since you have been promoted to Concubine,
all your female relatives should also be honored.
I gave the order to grant your mother the third noble rank.
I humbly thank Your Majesty.
My mother was the only female holder of the third noble rank.
Now Concubine Sourire's mother
has risen to the same rank.
Perhaps His Majesty did it impulsively.
I don't think so.
When His Majesty had agreed to further
promote my mother, to second noble rank,
the Empress opposed it strongly
saying that the mother of a Consort shouldn't hold a high rank.
So my mother is still third noble rank.
And Zhen Huan is just a Concubine.
She doesn't deserve this honor.
When her child is born, I'm afraid she
will be "treading on my face."
That won't happen.
Why not?
You have a child too.
But why are you still a Noble Lady
while she has already become a Concubine?
You are just as useless as ever!
Your Highness, please don't be angry.
It is not good for your health.
You want me to not be angry?
Only if she is eliminated.
My Lady.
I know what you want to say.
But life has to go on,
doesn't it?
I'm just worried about you, My Lady.
You don't need to worry about me.
I'm used to it.
You are the mother of the princess after all.
How can she shout at you like that?
All I wish is Wenyi will grow up peacefully.
Nothing else matters to me.
But Consort Fleur and Concubine Sourire have long been "enemies like water and fire".
You are caught in between ...
She knows how to yell at me to take down Concubine Sourire,
but not how difficult it is.
Her family is getting increasingly powerful.
If she gives birth to a prince, her
prestige will surpass Consort Fleur's.
My Lady, you have to think about yourself.
How?
Do I have a choice?
One day in the palace is just like another.
There's nothing new.
The Summer Palace was so much more fun.
The weather is so good today.
Let's go fly a kite, Sourire.
I kept two kites from your birthday.
You can't behave yourself even just for a day.
I heard you were playing jacks in your chamber
and broke an enamel vase His Majesty had awarded.
His Majesty won't blame me.
Sourire, stop reading, please.
Let's go out for a walk.
You've been doing nothing - staying in here all day.
What if my nephew becomes a lazy boy?
That's good. I have nothing interesting to do all day.
My Lady, you should avoid going out.
What happened to Lady Fuca is frightening.
We can have extra servants go with us.
Sourire, please. Let's go outside.
All right.
Sourire, am I a master kite flyer?
Yes, you are.
I liked flying kites a lot when I was home.
Yes, His Majesty said you would be promoted
to Noble Lady after the
Dragon Boat Festival for your excellent kite flying skills.
His Majesty likes you and that's why he likes me, isn't it?
Of course not, we all like you.
Sourire, do you like flying kites?
I do.
When I was practicing needlework at home,
I would always go fly kites with Meizhuang.
I will do that with your child.
If it's a princess, I hope she will be as lively as you are.
Ah, the line broke.
I'll go pick up the kite.
Follow her quickly.
Help her look for the kite.
No, don't follow me!
Sourire, they will just get in my way.
Follow her at a distance.
- Go, quickly!
- Yes, Your Highness.
My lady.
You're not allowed to go with me. Just wait here.
Yes, My Lady.
Rise.
I have a note here.
You must deliver it to the Great General in person.
Yes, Your Highness.
These people are seeking public offices.
Let the Great General decide
whether they can be used or not.
Yes. The Great General asked me to
be the messenger between him and Your Highness.
The Great General will take care of them for Your Highness.
Very well.
Tell the Great General that
we need to have our own people in the court.
So we can easily find opportunities to
get rid of those who displease us,
such as Concubine Sourire's father.
Yes, the Great General said
he didn't eliminate Concubine Sourire's father
for fear that it would disturb His Majesty.
I don't care about how or when he will do it.
I just want it to be done.
Don't worry, Your Highness. I will deliver the message.
No, it will make things worse if you shout at her.
Also, don't come to my palace.
We need to avoid people's attention.
I'll instruct you to come here if I need to see you.
Yes.
Keep your lips sealed.
Peace to Lady Cao.
Peace to Concubine Sourire.
Rise, Cao.
We don't have to stand on ceremony here.
I didn't expect to see Your Highness here.
Have a seat.
You speak so formally with me, Cao.
You can call me Sourire.
Sourire.
You have been very careful since you got pregnant.
Why would you send your servants away?
I like how you banter with me.
Since I’m with you,
if anything happens to me, it will be your responsibility.
You will certainly take full care of me.
Besides, no one else will push me from behind here.
You must be joking.
Why would anyone do that?
No one dares to even lay a finger upon you.
How is Princess Wenyi?
Thank you for asking.
Wenyi just had a slight cough. It's not a concern.
Certainly, as long as no cassava starch
is mixed into her diet,
she will be in good health.
His Majesty has already punished Xiao Tang,
who mixed up the ingredients.
I believe it won’t happen again.
I hope so, too.
I will be a mother soon.
I can understand how a mother feels.
You have been through a lot raising Wenyi.
I heard that you experienced difficult labor
and it was very dangerous.
Yes.
It's not at all easy being a mother.
There's something to worry about all the time.
Any suffering she has gouges my heart.
I wish I could suffer for her.
You are a smart mother
and know how to raise the princess.
But I have to say this.
It's good to be protected by someone, but
it doesn't mean they won't harm you.
And when they do, you find yourself
enduring the suffering in silence.
I’m a slow-witted person. I don't quite understand.
If you don't, me neither.
But here's something I know.
When Consort Fleur was punished for
trying to enter Meizhuang's confinement chamber,
it was because someone gave her a push.
Although it wasn't intended as a favor
for me, I still appreciated the help.
I also know another thing.
No good will come to either "the tiger or the jackal".
"Forsake darkness and come into the light"
is the best way to protect oneself and others.
“A smart bird chooses the tree to perch on.”
Your Highness,
go check the side of the mountain.
Come here!
Why hasn’t Attendant Chun come back yet?
Aren’t there some eunuchs following her?
Send more people to look for her. Go!
Let's go!
Did you find her?
Yes ...
That's good.
She must be hungry now.
- Is the dessert ready?
- Yes.
- Go get it.
- Aye.
What’s wrong?
Was she punished or something?
My Lady ...
Attendant Chun ...
Attendant Chun drowned in the lotus pond.
When we found her,
there was still a piece of the kite string in her hand.
My Lady!
She was hopping around flying the kite this afternoon.
How could she have drowned in the lotus pool?
She’s just seventeen!
My Lady…
We were just talking and laughing this afternoon.
I said after the Dragon Boat Festival,
His Majesty will promote her to Noble Lady.
She was having the snacks I prepared for her.
She was saying
she would be the aunt of my child.
She gave me the bracelet as a deposit gift.
My Lady, please calm down.
Your Highness ...
Attendant Chun has been enshrined
in the Rain Flower Pavilion.
[the biggest temple in the palace]
My Lady!
Go after My Lady! She shouldn't be running!
My Lady! My Lady!
My Lady, slow down!
My Lady!
My Lady, you must not go!
His Majesty sent her to the Rain Flower Pavilion
because it's not good for you to see her.
Please pardon my offence!
You must not go, My Lady!
Please calm down, My Lady.
You will disturb His Majesty if you go.
For the good of the child, you must not go!
My Lady!
His Majesty the Emperor.
Your Majesty.
Huan Huan, don't be sad.
It was all my fault!
I shouldn't have agreed to fly a kite with her.
I shouldn't have let her go pick up the kite all by herself.
Your Majesty.
Boil some herbal sleep aids.
Yes.
I am deeply saddened by her untimely passing.
I will grant her the posthumous honor
to be titled Noble Lady.
Her funeral will follow the imperial
protocol for a Noble Lady.
Your Majesty, I'm begging of you.
Please allow me to see Chun'er for the last time.
Your Majesty.
It was nicely done. You were fast and efficient.
Not a hair out of place.
You will be well rewarded.
It's an honor to do anything for Your Highness.
I don't desire any more rewards.
I received Heaven's aid.
Had I not noticed her, it would have ended
that source of income for me and my brother.
That would spoil the big plan.
Your Highness is greatly blessed by Heaven.
No one can hinder Your Highness.
That girl was just another vixen.
Zhen Huan must be saddened to death now.
It feels good to see her eyes full of tears.
Even if Concubine Sourire is having her moment,
how can she ever compare to
Your Highness's distinguished status?
My Lady, please don't dwell overly on it.
It's not what any one had hoped.
Hey.
Mist?
Your Highness, please bring justice to My Lady!
What do you mean?
My Lady ...
My Lady was murdered.
What are you talking about?
My Lady grew up by the water.
She's a good swimmer and would never drown.
I don't believe it was an accident.
Jinxi.
You've asked the servants who followed Chun'er this afternoon.
What did they say?
They all said Attendant Chun ran away too fast
to the other side of the rockery mountain.
They were not able to follow her.
And they found her in the pond when
they were asked to search for her.
Everyone said she lost her footing and fell into the pond.
Now that doesn't seem to be true.
When Lady Cao told me to check in the garden ...
Did she know about it?
Or she showed up ...
just to delay us?
Delay me from sending people to search.
I have to go ask her.
My Lady,
She won't say anything even if you go now.
I can't do anything if we don't have any evidence.
If Chun'er was murdered,
I will seek vengeance for her.
The murderer will get what they deserve.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.